this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
ski radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society IEEE software Magazine
online at computer.org software
today I'm talking to Z ISO they're the
archmage of infrastructure at tailscale
and they also have a great blog everyone
should check out Z welcome to software
engineering radio thanks it's great to
be here I think the first thing we
should start with is what's a VPN
because I think some people they may
have used it to remote into their
workplace or something like that but I
think the scope of what it's good for
and what it does is a lot broader than
that so maybe you could talk a little
bit about that first okay a VPN is short
for virtual private Network it's
basically a fake Network that's overlaid
on top of existing networks and then you
can use that Network to do whatever you
would with a normal computer network
this term has been co-opted by companies
that are attempting to get into the like
hide my style Market where you know you
encrypt your internet information and
keep it safe from hackers so it makes it
really annoying and hard to talk about
what a VPN actually is because tailscale
the company I work for is closer to like
the actual intent of a VPN and not just
you know like hide your internet traffic
that's already encrypted anyway with
another level of encryption and just
make a great access point for uh three
letter agencies but are there use cases
past that like when you're developing a
piece of software why would you decide
to use a VPN outside of just because I
want my you know my workers to be able
to get access to this stuff
so something that's come up when I've
been working at tailscale is that
sometimes we'll make changes to
something and it will be changes to like
the user experience of something on the
admin panel or something
so in a lot of other places I've worked
in order to have other people test that
you know you'd have to push it to the
cloud it would have to spin up a review
app in Heroku or some terrifying
terraform Abomination would have to put
it out onto like an actual cluster or
something but with tailscale if your app
is running locally you just give like
the name of your computer in the port
number and other people are able to just
see it and poke it and experience it and
that basically turns the feedback cycle
from like having to wait for like the
state of the world to converge to make a
change press F5 give the URL to a
co-worker and be like hey is this Gucci
they can connect to your app as if you
were both connected to the same switch
you don't have to worry about pushing to
a cloud service or opening ports things
like that yep it will act like it's in
the same room even when they're not
it'll even work if you're both at a
Starbucks and the Starbucks has
reasonable policies like holy crap don't
allow devices to connect to each other
directly so you're working on like your
screenplay app at your Starbucks or
something and you have a co-worker there
and you're like hey check this out and
give them the link and then you know
they're also seeing the screenplay
editor in terms of security and things
like that I'm picturing it kind of like
we were sitting in the same room and
there's a switch and we both plugged in
normally when you do something like that
you kind of have full access to whatever
else is on the switch you know provided
it's not being blocked by a firewall is
there like a layer of security on top of
that that a VPN service like tailscale
would provide yes there are these things
called Access Control lists which are
kind of like firewall rules except you
don't have to deal with like the
nightmare of writing an iptables rule
that also works in Windows firewall and
whatever they use in Mac OS the Apple
rules are applied at the tailnet level
for every device in the tail net so if
you have like developer machines you can
put people into groups as things like
developers and say that developer
machines can talk to production but not
people in QA they can only talk to
testing and people on SRE have you know
permissions to go everywhere and people
within their own teams can connect to
each other you can make more complicated
policies like that fairly easily and
when we think about infrastructure for
companies you were talking about how
there could be development
infrastructure production infrastructure
and you kind of separate it all out when
you're working with Cloud infrastructure
a lot of times there's the I always
forget what it stands for but there's
like IAM there's like policies that you
can set up with the cloud provider that
says these users can access this or
these machines can access this and I
wonder from your perspective when you
would choose to use that versus use
something at the network or the VPN
level the way I think about it is that
things like IAM enforce permissions
for like more granularly scoped things
like can create ec2 instances or can
delete ec2 instances or something like
that and that's just kind of a different
level of thing tailscale apples are more
you know X is allowed to connect to y or
with tailscale SSH X is allowed to
connect as user Y and that's really
different than like arbitrary capability
things like IAM offers you could think
about it as an IAM system but the main
permissions of this exposing are can x
connect to Y on Z Port what are some
other use cases where if you weren't
using a VPN you'd have to do a lot more
work or there's a lot more complexity
kind of what are some cases where it's
like okay using a VPN here makes a lot
of sense there is a service internal
detail scale called go which is a clone
of Google's so-called go links where
it's basically a URL shortener that
lives at HTTP colon slash go so and you
know you have Go slash something to get
to some internal admin service or
another thing to get to like you know
the company directory in notion or
something and this kind of thing you
could do with a normal setup you know
you could set it up and have to do oauth
challenges everywhere and have to make
sure that everyone has the right DNS
configuration so that it shows up in the
right place and then you'd have to deal
with https because oauth requires https
for understandable and kind of important
reasons and it's just a mess like
there's so many layers of stuff like the
barrier to get you know like just a darn
URL shortener up turns from like 20
minutes into three days of effort trying
to you know understand how these various
Arcane things work together you need to
have state for your oauth implementation
you need to worry about what the hell a
jot is it's just bad and I really think
that something like tailscale with
everybody has an IP address in order to
get into the network you have to sign in
with your auth provider your auth
provider tells tailscale who you are so
transitively every IP address is tied to
an owner which means that you can
enforce access permission based on the
IP address and the metadata about it
that you grab from the tailscale Daemon
it's just so much simpler like you don't
have to think about oh how do I set up
oauth this time what the hell is no auth
proxy what is a kubernetes that sort of
thing you just think about like doing
the thing and you just do it and then
everything else gets taken care of it's
like kind of the ultimate Network
infrastructure because it's both
omnipresent and something you don't have
to think about and I think that's really
the power of Tails tale typically when
you would spin up a service that you
want your developers or your system
admins to be able to log into you would
have to have some way of authenticating
and authorizing that user and so you
were talking about bringing oauth and
having your your service understand that
but I guess what you're saying is that
when you have something like tailscale
that's kind of front loaded I guess you
authenticate with tailscale you get onto
the network you get your IP and then
from that point on you can access all
these different services that know like
hey because you're on the network we
know you're authenticated and those
Services can just maybe map that IP
that's not going to change to like users
in some kind of table and not have to
worry about figuring out how do I
authenticate this user I would
personally more suggest that you use the
who is lookup or out in the tailscale
Damon's local API but basically yeah you
don't really have to worry too much
about like the authentication layer
because the authentication layer has
already been done you know you've
already done your two factor with Gmail
or whatever and then you can just
transitively push that property onto
your other machines so when you talk
about this who is Damon can you give an
example of I'm in the network now I'm
going to make a service call to an
application what am I doing with this
who is Damon it's more of like a turtle
API call that we expose via tailscale
D's Unix socket but basically you give
it an IP address and a port and it tells
you who the person is it's kind of like
the Unix ident protocol in a way except
completely not and at a high level you
know if you have something like a proxy
for grafana you have that proxy for
grafana make a call to the local
tailscale David and be like hey who is
this person and the telescale demon will
spit back at Json object like oh it's
this person on this device and there you
can do additional logic like maybe you
shouldn't be allowed to delete things
from an iOS device you know crazy ideas
like that there's not really support for
like arbitrary capabilities and tail
scale D at the time of recording but
we've had some thoughts would be cool
would that also include things like
having roles for example even if it's
just strings that you get back so that
your application would know okay this
person is supposed to have admin access
to this service based on what I got back
from this service not currently you can
probably do it via convention or
something but what's currently
implemented in the actual like source
code and user experience that you can't
do that right now it is something that
I've been trying to think about
different ways to solve but it's also a
problem that's a bit big for me
personally to tackle there's so many I I
guess different ways of doing it that
it's kind of interesting to think of a
solution that's kind of built into the
network yeah yeah
and when I describe that authentication
thing to some people it makes them
recoil in shock
because there's kind of a Stockholm
syndrome type effect with security for a
lot of things where the easy way to do
something and the secure way to do
something are you know like completely
opposite and directly conflicting with
each other in almost every way and over
time people have come to associate
Security or like corporate vpns as
annoying complicated and difficult and
the idea of something that isn't
annoying complicated or difficult will
make people reject it like just on
principle because you know they've been
trained that you know VPN equals virtual
pain Network and it's hard to get that
Association out of people's heads
because you know a lot of vpns are
virtual paying networks like I used to
work for Salesforce and Salesforce had
this corporate VPN where no matter what
you did all of your traffic would go out
to the internet from their data center I
think it was in San Francisco or
something and I was in the Seattle area
so whenever I had the VPN on my latency
to Google shot up by like eight times
and being a software person you know I
use Google the same way that others
breathe and it was just not fun and I
only had the VPN on for the bare minimum
of when I needed it and oh God it was so
bad
like some people when they picture a VPN
they picture exactly what you're
describing where all of my traffic is
going to get routed to Some central
point it's going to go connect to the
thing for me and then send the result
back so maybe you could talk a little
bit about why that's maybe a wrong
assumption I guess in the case of tail
scale or maybe in the case of just more
modern VPN Solutions yeah so the thing
that I was describing is what I've been
lovingly calling the single point of
failure as a service type model of VPN
where you know you have like the big
server somewhere it concentrates all the
connections and you know like does
things to make the computer feel like
they've teleported over there but
overall it's a single point of failure
and if that falls over you know like
goodbye VPN everybody's just totally
screwed and in contrast tailscale does a
more peer-to-peer thing so that everyone
is based basically on equal footing
everyone can send traffic directly to
each other and if it can't get directly
to there it'll use a network of uh relay
servers lovingly called derp and you
don't have to worry about your single
point of failure in your cluster because
there's just no single point of failure
everything will directly communicate as
much as possible and if it can't it'll
still communicate anyway let's say I
start up my computer and I want to
connect to a server in a data center
somewhere at the very beginning am I
connecting to some server hosted at
tailscale and then there's some kind of
negotiation process where after that I
connect directly or do I just connect
directly straight away if you just turn
on your laptop and log in it signs into
tailscale and gets you on the tail net
and whatnot then it will actually start
all connections via derp just so that it
can negotiate the uh direct connection
and in case it can't you know it's
already connected via derp so it just
continues the connection with derp and
this creates a kind of seamless magic
type experience where doing things over
derp is slower yes it is measurably
slower because you know like you're not
going directly you're doing TCP inside
of TCP and you know that comes with the
average Minefield of lasers or whatever
you call it and it does work though it's
not ideal if you want to do things like
copy large amounts of data but if you
just want to SSH into prod and see the
Vlogs for what the heck is going on and
while you're getting page at 3am it's
pretty great which you were calling derp
is it where you have servers kind of all
over the world and somehow it determines
which ones I guess is it which one's
closest to your destination or which
one's closest to you I'm gonna it's
really interesting it's one of the most
weird distributed systems type things
that I've ever seen it's the kind of
thing that could only come out of the
mind of an ex-googler but basically
every tail scale node has a connection
to all of The Derp servers and through
process of you know latency testing it
figures out which connection is the
fastest and the lowest latency and it
calls that it's home derp but because
everything is connected to every derp
you can have two people with different
home derps getting their packets relayed
to other clients from different derps so
you know if you have a laptop in Ottawa
and a laptop in San Francisco the laptop
in San Francisco will probably use the
uh derp that's closest to it but the
laptop in Ottawa will also use the dirt
that's closest to it so you get this
sort of like asynchronous thing and it
actually works out a lot better in
practice than you're probably imagining
and then these servers what was the
technical term for them are they like
relays or what's the relays they only
really deal with encrypted wire guard
packets and there's no way for us at
tail scale to see the contents of dirt
messages it is literally just a
forwarder it literally just forwards
Things based on the key ID
I guess if tailscale isn't able to
decrypt the traffic is that because the
keys are only on the user's devices like
it's on their laptop and on the server
they're trying to reach or yeah the
private keys are live and die with those
devices or the devices they were minted
on and the public keys are given to the
coordination server and the coordination
server spreads those around to every
device in your telnet it does some
limiting so that like if you don't have
apple access to something you don't get
the public key for it the public key not
the private key the public key not the
private key and then you know you just
go that way and it'll just figure it out
it's pretty nice when we're kind of
talking about situations where it can't
connect directly that's where you would
use the relay what are kind of the
typical cases where that happens where
you aren't able to just connect directly
Hotel Wi-Fi and paranoid network
security setups Hotel Wi-Fi is the most
notorious this one because you know you
have like an overpriced Wi-Fi connection
and if you bring like I don't know like
you're recording a bunch of footage on
your iPhone and because in 2022 the
iPhone has the USB 2 connection on it
and you know you want to copy that you
want to use the network but you can't so
you could just let it upload through
iCloud or something or do the bare
minimum you need to get the data off
with derp it wouldn't be ideal but it
would work and ironically enough that
entire complexity involved with you know
doing TCP inside of TCP to copy a video
file over to your laptop might actually
be faster than USB 2 which is something
that I did the math for a while ago and
I just started laughing that is pretty
pretty ridiculous welcome to the Future
man
in terms of connecting directly usually
when you have a computer on the internet
you don't have all your ports open you
don't necessarily allow just anybody to
send you traffic over UDP and so forth
let's say I want to send
UDP data to a server on my network but
you know maybe it has some TCP ports
open I'm assuming once I connect into
the network via the VPN I'm able to use
other protocols and ports that weren't
necessarily exposed is that correct yeah
you can use UDP you can do basically
anything you would do on a normal
Network except multicast because
multicast is weird I mean there's
thoughts on how to handle multicast but
the main problem is that like wireguard
which is what a tail scale is built on
top of is so-called OSI model layer 3
Network where it's at like you know the
IP address level and multicast is a
layer 2 or data link layer type thing
and those are different numbers and you
can't really easily put like broadcast
packets into IP ipv4 thinks otherwise
but in practice no people don't actually
use the broadcast address so for someone
who's they have a project or their
company wants to get started I mean what
does onboarding look like what do they
have to do to get all these devices
talking to one another basically you
install tailscale
you log in with a little GUI thing or on
a Linux server you run tailscale up and
then you all log into a like a g Suite
account with the same domain name so you
know if your domain is like example.com
then everybody logs in with their
example.com G Suite account and there is
no step three everything is allowed and
everything can just connect and you can
change the permissions from there by
default the apples are set to a you know
very permissive allow everyone to talk
to everyone on any port just so that
people can verify that it's working you
know you can ping to your heart's
content you can play Minecraft with
others you can host an HTTP server you
can SSH into your development box and
write blog posts with emacs whatever you
want okay you install the software on
your servers your workstations your
laptops and so on and then after that
there's some kind of web page or
dashboard you would go in and say I want
these people to be able to access these
things and these ports and so on you can
customize the access control rules with
something that looks like Json but with
trailing commas and comments allowed and
you can go from there to customize
basically anything to your heart's
content you can set rules so that people
on the devops team can access everything
but you know maybe marketing doesn't
need access to the production database
so you don't have to worry about that as
much there's been different I guess you
would call them VPN protocols I mean
there's people have probably worked with
ipsec in some situations they may have
heard of openvpn wireguard in the case
of tail scale I believe you chose to
build it on top of wireguard so I wonder
if you could talk a little bit about
why you chose wireguard and maybe what
makes it unique I wasn't on the team
that initially wrote like the core of
tailscale itself but from what I
understand wire guard was chosen because
what overhead it's literally you just
encrypt the packets you send it to the
other server the other server decrypts
them and you know you're done it's also
based purely on the key pairs involved
and from what I understand like at the
wire guard protocol level there's no
reason why you would need an IP address
at all in theory but in practice you
kind of need an IP address because you
know everything sucks but
also wireguard is like UDP only which I
think it's like core implementation
which is a step up from like any connect
and open VPN where they have TCP modes
so you can experience the Glorious trash
fire of TCP and TCT and from what I
understand with wireguard you don't need
to set up a certificate Authority or
figure out how the heck to revoke
certificates you just have key Pairs and
if a node needs to be removed you delete
the key pair and you're done and I think
that really matches up with a lot of the
philosophy behind how tailscale networks
work a lot better you know you have a
list of keys
and if the network changes the list of
keys changes that's the end of the story
so maybe one of the big selling points
was just what has the least amount of
things I guess to deal with or what's
the simplest when you're using a
component that you want to put into your
own product you kind of want
the least amount of things that could go
wrong I guess yeah it's more like simple
but not like limiting like for example a
set of Tinker Toys is simple in that you
know you can build things that you don't
have to worry too much about the
material science but a set of Tinker
Toys is also limiting because you know
like they're little wooden dowels and
little circles made out of wood that you
stick the dowels into you know you can
only do so much with it and I think that
in comparison wire guard is simple you
know there's just key pairs they're just
encryption and it's simple and it's like
overall Theory and it's implementation
but it's not limiting like you can do
pretty much anything you want with it
inherently whenever we build something
that's what we want but that's an
interesting way of putting it yeah yeah
it can be kind of annoyingly hard to
figure out how to make things as simple
as they need to be but still allow for
complexity to occur so you don't have to
like set up a keyboard macro to write if
error not equals nil over and over I
guess the next thing I'd like to talk a
little bit about is we've covered it a
little bit but at a high level I
understand that tailscale uses wire
guard which is the open source VPN
protocol I guess you could call it and
then there's the client software you're
saying you need to install on each of
the servers and workstations but there's
also a control plane and I wonder if you
could kind of talk a little bit about I
guess at a high level what are all the
different components of tail scale
there's the agent that you install on
your devices the agent is basically the
same between all the devices it's all
written and go and turns out that go can
actually cross compile fairly well
so you have you know your implementation
in go that is basically the same code
more or less running on Windows Mac OS
FreeBSD Android Chrome OS iOS Linux I
think I just listed all the platforms
I'm not sure but you have that and then
there's the sort of control plane on
tailscale side the control plane is
basically like control which is I think
a get smart reference
and that is basically a key Dropbox so
you know you authenticate through there
that's where the admin panel is hosted
and that's what tells the different tail
scale nodes the keys of all the other
machines on the tailnet and also on
tailscale side there's derp which is the
fleet of a bunch of different vps's and
various clouds all over the world both
to try to minimize cost and to have
resiliency because if both digital ocean
and vulture go down globally we probably
have bigger problems I believe you
mentioned the the clients were written
in go are the control plane and the
relay the dirt portion are those also
written and go are they they're all
written and go yeah go as much as
possible yeah it's kind of what happens
when you have some X go team members as
the core people involved in tailscale
like there is a go compiler Fork that
has some additional patches that go
Upstream either can't except won't
accept or hasn't yet accepted for a
while it was how we did things like
trying to shave off bites from binary
size to attempt to fit it into the iOS
Network extension limit because for some
reason they only allowed you to have 15
megabytes of RAM for both like your
application and working Ram
and it turns out that 15 megabytes of
RAM is way more than enough to do
something like openvpn but you know when
you have a peer-to-peer VPN engine it
doesn't really work that well so a lot
of interesting engineering challenges
that was specifically for iOS so to run
it on an iPhone yeah and amazingly after
the person who did all of the
optimization to the Linker trying to get
the binary size down as much as possible
like replacing Unicode packages with
something that's more code efficient you
know like basically all but compressing
parts of the binary to try to save space
then the iOS I think 15 beta dropped and
we found out that they increased the
network extension Ram limit to 50
megabytes and the look of defeat on that
poor person's face I feel very bad for
him you got what you wanted but you're
sad about it yeah so that's interesting
too if you were using a fork of the go
compiler basically everything that is
built is built using the tailscale fork
of the go compiler going for it is the
sort of assumption is that's what you'll
do or is it you're hoping you can get
this stuff upstreamed and then
eventually move off of it I'm pretty
sure that I don't know if I can really
make a forward-looking statement like
that but I've come to accept the fact
that there's a fork at the Go compiler
and as a result it allows
a lot more experimentation and a bit
more control over what's going on I'm
not like the most happy with it but I
understand why it exists and I've made
my piece with it and I suppose it helps
somewhat that the people who are working
on it actually originally worked on the
go compiler at Google is that right oh
yeah if there weren't X go team people
working on that then I would definitely
feel way less comfortable about it but I
trust that the people that are working
on it know what they're doing at least
enough I feel like that's kind of the
position we put ourselves in with
software in general right is like do we
trust ourselves enough to do this thing
we're doing yeah and trust is a I
think one of the things that's
interesting about tailscale is that it's
a product that's kind of it's like
Network infrastructure right it's to
connect you to your other devices
and that's a little different than
somebody running a software as a service
and so how do you test something that's
like built to support a network and how
is that different than just making a web
app or something like that well it's a
lot more complicated for one especially
when you have to have multiple devices
in the mix with multiple different
operating systems and I was working on
some integration tests doing stuff for a
while and it was really complicated you
have to spin up virtual machines you
know you have to like make sure the
virtual machines are attempting to
download the version of the tailscale
client you want to test and it's quite a
lot in practice I mean do you have a lab
you know with Android phones and iPhones
and laptops and all this sort of stuff
and you have some kind of automated test
Suite to see like hey if these machines
are in Ottawa and my servers in San
Francisco like you mentioning before
that I can get from my iPhone to this
server in the data center over here that
kind of thing what's the right way to
phrase this without making things look
bad it's a work in progress It's really
a hard problem to solve especially when
the company is fully remote and like the
address that's listed on the business
records is literally one of the founders
condos because you know the company has
no office
so that makes the logistics for a lot of
this even more fun probably any company
that's in an early stage feels the same
way where it's like everything's a work
in progress and we're just gonna we're
gonna keep going and we're gonna get
there and as long as everything keeps
running we're good yeah I don't like
thinking about it in that way because it
kind of sounds like pessimistic or
defeatist but at some level it's it
really is a work in progress because
it's a hard problem and hard problems
take a lot of time to solve especially
if you want a solution that you're happy
with and I think it's kind of a unique
case too where it's not like if it goes
down it's like people can't do their job
right so it's yeah actually if tail
skills like control playing goes down I
don't think people would notice until
they tried to like reboot a laptop or
connect a new device to their tail net
because once all the tailscale agents
have all the information they need from
the control plane you know they just
continue on independently and don't have
to care derp is also fairly independent
of the like the key Dropbox component
and you know if that goes down derp
doesn't care at all okay okay so if the
control plane is down as long as you had
authenticated earlier in the day you can
still I don't know if it's cached or
something but you can still continue to
reach the relay servers The Derp servers
or your other nodes yeah yeah I'm pretty
sure that in most cases the control
plane could be down for several hours a
day and nobody would notice unless
they're trying to deal with the admin
panel got it that's a little bit of a
relief I suppose for all of you running
it yeah it's also kind of hard to sell
people on the idea of here is a VPN
thing you don't need to self-host it and
they're like what why and yeah
can't be fun though I mean I feel like
anybody who has self-hosted a VPN they
probably like don't really want to do it
I don't know maybe I'm wrong so a lot of
the idea of wanting to self-host it is I
think it's more of like trying to be
self-sufficient and not have to rely on
other companies failures dictating your
company's downtime and you know like
from some level that's very
understandable and you know if tailscale
were to get bought out and the new
owners would like basically kill the
product they'd still have something that
would work for them I don't know if like
such a defeatist attitude is like
productive but it is certainly the
opinion that I have received when I have
asked people why they want to self-host
other people don't want to deal with
identity providers or the like they want
to use their own identity provider and
what was hilarious was there was one
thing where they were like our old VPN
server died once and we got locked out
of our Network so therefore we want to
self-host tailscale in the future so
that this won't happen again and I'm
like buddy let's just take a moment and
retrace the steps here because I don't
think you mean what you think you mean
yeah yeah
in general like I suggest people that
you know even if they're like way deep
you could do the tail scale Kool-Aid
they still have at least one other
method of getting into their servers
ideally too I admit that I come from an
SRE style background and I am way more
paranoid than most but I usually like
having a backup just in case so I
suppose on that note let's talk a little
bit about your role at tail skill the
title of the archmage of infrastructure
is one of the coolest titles I've I've
seen so maybe you can go a little bit
into what that entails at tailscale I
started that title as a joke that kind
of stuck my initial intent was that
every time someone asked I'd say I'd
have a different you know like Mystic
sounding title but archmage of
infrastructure kind of stuck and since
then I've actually been pivoting more
into developer relations stuff rather
than pure software engineering and from
the feedback that I've gotten at the
various conferences I spoke in at they
like that title even though it doesn't
really fit with developer relations work
at all it's like it fits because it
doesn't you know that kind of Coney kind
of way I guess this would go more into
the infrastructure side but what does
the scale of your infrastructure look
like I mean I think that you touched a
little bit on the fact that you have
relay servers all over the place and
you've got this control plane but I
wonder if you could give people a little
bit of perspective of what kind of
undertaking this is I am pretty sure at
this point we have more developer
laptops and the like than we do
production servers I'm pretty sure that
the scale of production servers are in
the tens at most it turns out that
computers are pretty darn efficient and
you don't really need like a lot of
computers to do something amazing the
part that I guess surprises me a little
bit is the relay servers I suppose
because I would imagine there's a lot of
traffic that goes through those are you
finding that just most of the time they
just aren't needed and usually you can
make a direct connection and that's why
you don't need too many of these from
what I understand I don't know if we
actually have a way to tell like what
percentage of data is going over the
relays versus not
and I think that was an intentional
decision that may have been Revisited
and operating based off of like six to
12 month old information right now but
in general the only state that the relay
servers has is in Ram and whenever you
disconnect the state is dropped and even
then that state is like you know this
key is listening it is connected in case
you want to send packets over here I
guess it's a bit less bandwidth than
you're probably thinking it's not like
enough to Max it out 24 7 but it is
measurable and there are some costs
associated with it this is also why it's
on digitalocean and vulture and not AWS
but in general it's a lot less than
you'd think I'm pretty sure that like if
I had to give a baseless assumption I'd
say that probably about like 85 of
traffic goes directly and the remaining
is like the few cases in the hole
punching engine that we haven't figured
out yet like Palo Alto firewalls oh God
those things are a nightmare I see so
it's most of the traffic actually ends
up being straight peer-to-peer doesn't
have to go through your infrastructure
and therefore it's like you don't need
too many machines to make this whole
thing work yeah it turns out the
computers are pretty darn fast and that
copying data is something that computers
are really good at doing so if you have
you know some pretty darn fast computers
basically just sitting there and copying
data back and forth all day like you can
do a lot with shockingly little when I
first started I believe that the Derp
VMS were using like sometimes as little
as one core and 512 megabytes of ram as
like a primary derp and we only noticed
when there were some weird connection
issues for people that were only on derp
because there were enough users that the
machine had ran out of memory so we just
you know upped the uh virtual machine
size and called it a day but it's truly
remarkable how far you can get with very
little and you mentioned the relay
servers The Derp servers were on
services like digitalocean and vulture
I'm assuming because of the bandwidth
costs for the control plane is that on
AWS or some other big cloud provider
it's on AWS I believe it's in EU Central
one you're helping people connect from
device to device and in a situation like
that what does monitoring look like in
incidents like what are you looking for
to determine like hey something's not
working
there's monitoring with you know
Prometheus grafana all of that stuff
there are some external probing things
there's also some continuous functional
testing for trying to connect to
tailscale and like log in as an account
and if that fails like twice in a row
then you know something's very wrong and
you know raise the alarm but in general
a lot of our monitoring is kind of hard
at some levels because we're tail scale
tail scale can't always benefit from
tail scale to help operate tailscale
because you know it's tail skill so
still trying to figure out how to
detangle the chicken and egg situation
it's really annoying there's the term
dog fooding right where they're saying
like oh we run our own development on
our own platform or our own software but
I could see when your product is Network
infrastructure vpns where that could be
a little a little dicey yeah it is very
annoying but I'm pretty sure we'll
figure something out this is just a
matter of when another thing that's come
up is we've kind of wanted to use tail
skills SSH features where you'd specify
Ackles rules to allow people to SSH into
other nodes as various users but if that
becomes your main access to production
then you know like if tailscale is down
and your tail scale how do you get in
then there's been various philosophical
discussions about this it's also
slightly worse if you use what's called
check mode in SSH where tailcl SSH
without check mode you know you just the
server checks against the policy rules
in the apple and if it's okay it lets
you in and if not it says no but with
check mode there's also this like eight
hour quote unquote lifetime for you to
have like pseudo mode on GitHub where
you do an auth challenge with your auth
provider and then you know you're given
a uh hey this person has done this thing
type verification and if that's down and
that goes through the control plane and
if the control plane is down and your
tail scale trying to debug the control
plane and in order to get into the
control plane over tail scale you need
to use the control plane you know that's
like chicken and egg problem level 78.
which is a mythical level of chicken egg
problem that has only been foretold in
the Legends of your or something at that
point it sounds like somebody just needs
to drive to the data center and plug
into the switch
I mean it probably wouldn't be like you
know we need to get a person with an
angle grinder off of Craigslist type pad
like it was with the Facebook bgp outage
but it's definitely a chicken and egg
problem in its own right it makes you do
a lot of lateral thinking too which is
also kind of interesting when you say
lateral thinking I'm just kind of
curious if you have an example of what
you mean I don't know of any example
that is an ND aid but basically you know
tailscale is getting to the point where
tail scale is relying on tail scale to
make tail skill function and you know
yeah this is classic uravoro style
problem I've heard a uh wise friend of
mine said that that is an ideal problem
to have which sounds weird at face value
but if you're getting to that point that
means that you're successful enough that
you're having that problem which is in
itself a good thing paradoxically better
to have that problem than to have nobody
care about the product right yeah
kind of on that note you mentioned you
worked at Salesforce I believe that was
working on Heroku I wonder if you could
talk a little about your experience
working at you know tail scale which is
kind of more of a you know early startup
versus an established company like
Salesforce so at the time I was working
at Heroku it definitely didn't feel like
I was working at Salesforce so the
majority of it it felt like I was
working you know at Heroku like on my
resume I listed as Heroku when I talked
about it to people I said I worked at
Heroku and that Salesforce was this you
know mythical Ohana thing that I didn't
have to deal with unless I absolutely
had to by the end of the time I was
working at hiroku the Salesforce sort of
started to creep in and you know we
moved from tracking issues in GitHub
issues like we were used to to using
their what's the polite way to say this
their creation which was like the moral
equivalent of jira implemented on top of
Salesforce you had to be behind the VPN
for it and you know every ticket had 20
fields and there were no templates and
in comparison with tailscale you know we
just use GitHub issues maybe some like
things in notion for doing like longer
term tracking or kanban stuff but it's
nice to not have
you know all of the Pomp and ceremony of
filling out 20 fields and a ticket for
like two sentences of this thing is
obviously wrong and it's causing X to
happen please fix I like that phrase the
the creation that's a very very
diplomatic term I mean I can think of
other ways to describe it but I'm pretty
sure those ways wouldn't be allowed on
the podcast so
but yeah I know what you mean for sure
where it feels like there's this
movement from hey let's just do what we
need like let's fill in the information
that's actually relevant and don't do
anything else to a shift to we need to
fill in these 10 Fields because that's
the thing we do yeah yeah and in the
time I've been working for tailskill I'm
like employee ID 12 and tailscale has
gone from a company where I literally
know everyone who just recently to the
point where I don't know everyone
anymore and it's a really weird feeling
I've never been in a like a small stage
startup that's gotten to this size
before and I've described some of my
feelings to other people who've been
there and they're like yeah welcome to
the club so I figure a lot of it is
normal from what I understand though
there's a lot of intentionality to try
to prevent tail skill from becoming you
know like Google style complexity
organizational complexity unless that is
absolutely necessary to do something
it's a function of size right like as
you have more people more teams then
more process comes in that's a really
tricky balance to grow and still
keep that feeling of I'm just doing the
thing I'm doing the work rather than all
this other process stuff yeah but I have
also kind of managed to pigeonhole
myself off and do a corner with devrel
stuff and that's been nice been working
a bunch with like marketing people and
helping out with support occasionally
and doing a god-awful amount of writing
the writing for our audience's benefit I
think they should really check out your
blog because I think that the way you
write your articles is very thoughtful
in terms of the balance of the actual
example code or example scripts and the
descriptions and there's a little bit of
a narrative sometimes too so I'm
actually more of a prose writer just by
like how I naturally write things
as we wrap up is there anything we
missed or anything else you want to
mention do you want to look at my blog
it's on Z iso.net that's
x-e-i-a-s-o.net that's where I post
things you can see like the 280
something articles at time of recording
it's probably going to get to 300 at
some point oh God it's going to get to
300 at some point and yeah I try to post
articles about weekly depending on facts
and circumstances I have a bunch of
talks coming up like one about the
hilarious over engineering I did in my
blog and maybe some more if I get back
positive responses from calls for paper
submissions I have a couple talks that
are gonna be up by the time this is
published one of them is my uh rust conf
on my what was it called I think it was
called The Surreal horrors of Pam or
something where I discuss my experience
try trying to plug a payout module in
Rust for work and it's the kind of story
where you know it's bad when you have a
break point on DL open that sounds like
a nightmare oh yeah like part of
attempting to fix that process involved
going very deep we're talking like an
HTML frame set in the internet archive
for sun OS documentation that was
written around the time that Pam was
used like things that are bad enough or
like everything in the frame set but the
contents had eroded away through bit rot
and you know you're very lucky just to
have what you do well I'm glad it was
you and not me we'll get to hear about
it and not have to go through the
suffering ourselves yeah one of the
things I've been telling people is that
I'm not like a brilliant programmer like
I know a bunch of people who are
definitely way smarter than me but what
I am is determined and determination is
a bit stronger of a force than you'd
think yeah I mean without it nothing
gets done right yeah very cool well Z
thank you so much for coming on software
engineering radio yeah thank you for
having me I hope you have a good day and
try out tailscale note my bias but I
think it's great this has been Jeremy
Jung for software engineering radio
thanks for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC
radio.slack.com you can also email us at
team sc-radio.net
this in all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening